<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A wise and moderate discourse, concerning church-affaires. As it was written, long since, by the famous authour of those considerations, which seem to have some reference to this. Now published for the common good.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E205_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212605</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871209</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76962)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 36:E205[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A wise and moderate discourse, concerning church-affaires. As it was written, long since, by the famous authour of those considerations, which seem to have some reference to this. Now published for the common good.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted in the yeere 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The famous authour" = Francis Bacon.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: quire B wrongly imposed, the text for p. 2-3 interchanged with p. 6-7.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "by Sr ffra: Bacon. Ld. Chancellor".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Wiſe and Moderate Diſcourſe, Concerning Church-Affaires. As it was written, long ſince, by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Authour of thoſe Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, which ſeem to have ſome reference to this. Now publiſhed for the common good.</p>
            <p>Imprinted in the yeere 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:157702:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:157702:2"/>
            <p>IT is but ignorance, if any man finde it ſtrange that the ſtate of Religion (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the dayes of peace) ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed and troubled with controverſies: for as it is the condition of the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant to be ever under trialls, ſo it commeth to paſſe that when the fiery triall of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ceaſeth, there ſucceedeth another triall, which as it were by contrary blaſtes of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, doth ſift and winow mens faith, and proveth them whether they know God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, even as the other of afflictions diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth whether they love him better then the world. Accordingly was it foretold by Chriſt, ſaying: <hi>That in the latter times it ſhould bee ſaid, Loe here, loe there is Chriſt;</hi> which is to be underſtood, not as if the very perſon of Chriſt ſhould bee aſſumed and counterfeited, but his authority and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence (which ought to bee truth it ſelfe) that ſhould bee chalenged and pretended. Thus have we read and ſeene to bee fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157702:3"/> that which followeth: <hi>Ecce in deſerto, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in penetratio:</hi> while ſome have ſought the truth in the conventicles and conciliables of Heretickes and Sectaries: others in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne face and repreſentation of the Church, and both ſorts been ſeduced. Were it then that the controverſies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were ſuch as did divide the unity of the Spirit, and not ſuch as doe unſwaddle her of her bands (the bands of peace) yet could it be no occaſion for any pretended Catholicke to judge us, or for any irreligious perſon to deſpiſe us: or if it be, it ſhall but happen to us all as it hath uſed to doe; to them to bee hardened, and to us to endure the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God. But now that our contentions are ſuch, as we need not ſo much that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Canon and ſentence of Chriſt: <hi>Erratis neſcientes Scripturas, &amp;c.</hi> as wee need the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of Saint <hi>Iames: Let every man bee ſwift to heare, ſlow to ſpeake, ſlow to wrath:</hi> And that the wound is no way dangerous, except wee poyſon it with our owne reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. As the former ſort of men have leſſe reaſon to make themſelves muſicke in our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157702:3"/> cord: ſo I have good hope that nothing ſhall diſpleaſe our ſelves which ſhall bee ſincerely and modeſtly propounded for the appeaſing of theſe diſſentions. For if any ſhall bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this voyce: <hi>Vos eſtis fratres,</hi> yee are brethren, why ſtrive yee? hee ſhall give great preſumption againſt himſelfe, that hee is the party that doth his brother wrong. The controverſies themſelves I will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into, as judging that diſeaſe requireth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſt then any other cure. Thus much we all know and confeſſe, that they bee not of the higheſt nature: for they are not touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the high myſteries of faith: ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Churches after their firſt peace for many yeares, what time the heretickes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved curious queſtions, and made ſtrange a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomies of the nature and perſon of Chriſt; and the Catholicke Fathers were compelled to follow them with all ſubtillity of diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and determinations, to exclude them from their evaſions, and to take them in their owne Labyrinths; ſo as it is rightly ſaid: <hi>Illis temporibus ingenioſa res fuit eſſe Chriſtianum:</hi> In thoſe dayes it was an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157702:4"/> and ſubtile matter to bee a Chriſtian: Neither are they concerning the great parts of the worſhip of God; of which it is true, that <hi>Non ſervatur unitas in credendo, niſi eadem adſit in colendo:</hi> There will bee kept no unity in beleeving, except it bee intire in worſhipping: ſuch as were the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies in the Eaſt and Weſt Churches touching Images, and ſuch as are many of thoſe which are betweene the Church of Rome and us, as about the adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sacrament, and the like. But wee contend about Ceremonies, and things indifferent, about the externe policie and government of the Church: In which kinde, if wee would but remember, that the ancient and true bonds of unity, are one Faith, one Baptiſme, and not one Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie, one Policie. If wee would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the league among Chriſtians, that is penned by our Saviour Chriſt <hi>(Hee that is not againſt us, is with us)</hi> if wee could but comprehend that ſaying, <hi>Differentia rituum commendat unitatem doctrinae:</hi> and that, <hi>Habet religio quae ſunt aeternitatis, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157702:4"/> quae ſunt temporis:</hi> Religion hath parts which belong to eternity, and parts which belong to time.</p>
            <p>And if wee did but know the vertue of ſilence, and ſlowneſſe to ſpeake, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> our controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies would (of themſelves) cloſe up and grow together. But moſt eſpecially, if we would leave the overweening and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent humours of theſe times, and renue the bleſſed proceedings of the Apoſtles and Fathers of the Primitive Church; which was in the like and greater caſes, not to enter into aſſertions and poſitions, but to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liver counſels and advices, we ſhould need no other remedy at all. <hi>Si cadem con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulis frater, qua affirmas, debetur conſulenti reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia, cum non debetur fides affirmanti:</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if that which you ſet downe by way of aſſertion, you would deliver by way of advice, there were reverence due to your counſell, where credit is not due to your affirmation. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was content to ſpeake thus: <hi>Ego, non Dominus;</hi> I, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157702:5"/> not the Lord: <hi>&amp; ſecundum conſilium meum,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ording to my counſell. But now men do ſo lightly ſay, Not I, but the Lord; yea, and binde it with heavie denunciations of his judgements, to terrifie the ſimple, which have not ſufficiently underſtood out of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that <hi>the cauſleſſe curſe ſhall not come:</hi> Therefore ſeeing the accidents are they which breed the perill, and not the things themſelves in their owne nature, it is meet the remedies bee applied unto them by ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what it is on either part that keepeth the wound greene, and formaliſeth both ſides to a further oppoſition, and worketh an indiſpoſition in mens mindes to be reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; wherein no accuſation is pretended. But I finde in reaſon, that it is beſt built by repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of wrongs, and in example that the ſpeeches which have been by the wiſeſt men, <hi>De concordia ordinum,</hi> have not abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from reducing to memory the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties uſed on both parts. So as it is true which was ſaid, <hi>Qui pacem tractat non repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titis conditionis: diſsidii, is magis animos dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedine pacis fallit quam aequitate componit.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:157702:5"/> And firſt of all, it is more then time that an end were made of this unmodeſt and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med kinde of writing lately entertained, whereby matters of religion are handled in the ſtile of the ſtage. Indeed bitter and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt writing is not haſtily to be condemned: for men cannot contend coldly and without affection about things they hold deare and pretious. A politicke man may write from his braine without touch or ſenſe of his heart, as in a ſpeculation that pertaineth not unto him; but a feeling Chriſtian will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe in his words a character either of zeale or love: the latter of which as I would wiſh ratherto be embraced, as being more fit for the times; yet is the former warranted alſo by great examples. But to leave all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and religious compaſſions toward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, or indignation toward faults, to turne religion into a Comedy or Satyr, to ſearch and rip up wounds with a laughing coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, to intermix Scripture and Scurrili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſometime in one ſentence, is a thing farre from the devour reverence of a Chriſtian, and ſcant beſeeming the honeſt regard of a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157702:6"/> ſober man. <hi>Non eſt major confuſio quam ſerii &amp; joci:</hi> there is no greater confuſion then the confounding of jeſt and earneſt. The majeſtie of religion, and the contempt and deformity of things ridiculous, are things as diſtant as things may be. Two principall cauſes have I ever knowne of Atheiſme, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious controverſies and prophane ſcoffing. Now that theſe two are joyned in one, no doubt that Sect will make no ſmall progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And here I do much eſteem the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and religion of that Biſhop, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the firſt pamphlet of this kinde, who remembred that a foole was to be anſwered, but not by becomming like unto him, and conſidered the matter hee handled, and not the perſon with whom he dealt. <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the majeſty and gravity of a Iudge in himſelfe, ſaith: <hi>If I did ſmile, they beleeved me not;</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid: If I diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or glanced unto conceit of mirth, yet mens mindes were ſo poſſeſſed with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of the action in hand, as they could not receive it. Much more ought this to be amongſt Biſhops and Divines diſputing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:157702:6"/> holy things: and therefore as much doe I miſlike of him, who as it ſeemed, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf with it, as no mean policie. That theſe men are to be dealt withall at their own weapons, and pledged in their owne cup. This (no doubt) ſeemed to him as profound, as when the Cardinall counſelled <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond to encounter the Councell of Nice with the Councell of Lateran; or as lawfull a chalenge as M. <hi>Iewell</hi> made to confute the pretended Catholicks by the Fathers.</p>
            <p>But theſe things will not excuſe the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of evill in another: It ſhould contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe be with us as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid: <hi>Nil malo quam eos ſimiles cum ſui, &amp; me mei.</hi> But now, <hi>dum de bonis contendimus, in malis conſentimus;</hi> while we differ in good things, we reſemble in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. Surely if I were asked of theſe men, who were the more to bee blamed, I ſhould perhaps remember the proverbe, <hi>That the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond blow maketh the fray;</hi> and the ſaying of an obſcure fellow, <hi>Qui replicat multiplicat,</hi> he that replieth multiplieth. But I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the queſtion with this ſtutterer: <hi>Alter principium malo dedit, alter modum abſtulit:</hi> by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:157702:7"/> the one means we have a beginning, by the other we ſhall have none end.</p>
            <p>And truely, as I doe marvell that ſome of thoſe preachers which do call for reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (whom I am farre from wronging, ſo farre as to joyne them with theſe ſcoffers) doe not publiſh ſome declaration, whereby they may ſatisfie the world, that they diſlike, their cauſe ſhould be ſo ſollicited: ſo I hope aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, that my Lords of the Cleargy have no intelligence with theſe other libellers; but do altogether diſallow that their dealing ſhould be thus defended: For though I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in him many glozes, whereby the man would inſinuate himſelfe into their favour; yet I finde too ordinary, that many preſſing &amp; fawning perſons, do miſconjecture of the humours of men in authority, and many times <hi>veneri immolant ſuem,</hi> they ſeeke to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie them with that they moſt diſlike. For I have great reaſon to ſatisfie my ſelfe touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the judgement of my Lords the Biſhops in this matter, by that which was written by one of them, whom I mentioned before with honour. Nevertheleſſe, I note, there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:157702:7"/> is not an indifferent hand carried toward theſe pamphlets as they deſerve. For the one ſort flieth in darkneſſe, and the other is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered openly. Wherein I might adviſe that ſide out of a wiſe writer, who hath ſet it downe, that <hi>punitis ingeniis gliſcit authoritas;</hi> and indeed we ever ſee it falleth out, that the forbidden writing is thought to be a certaine ſparke of truth that flieth up in the faces of them that feeke to choke and tread it out; whereas a booke authorized, is thought to bee but <hi>temporis voces,</hi> the language of the time. But in plaine truth I doe finde to my underſtanding, theſe pamphlets as meet to be ſuppreſſed as the others. Firſt, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer doe ſeeke to deface the government of the Church in the perſons of the Biſhops and Prelates: ſo the other doth lead into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the exerciſe of religion in the perſons of ſundry Preachers; ſo as it diſgraceth the higher matter, though in the meaner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Next, I finde certaine indiſcreet and dangerous amplifications, as if the civill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment if ſelfe of this eſtate, had neere loſt the force of its ſinewes, and were ready to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:157702:8"/> enter into ſome convulſion, all things being full of faction and diſorder; which is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſely acknowledged as untruly affirmed. I know his meaning is to inforce this unreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and violent impugning of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Biſhops, to bee a ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted fore-runner of a more generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
            <p>And I grant there is a ſympathy between both the eſtates: but no ſuch matter in the civill policie as deſerveth a taxation ſo diſhonourable. To conclude this point: As it were to bee wiſhed that theſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings had been abortive, and never ſeene the Sunne; ſo the next is, that ſeeing they be common abroad, that they bee cenſured of all that have underſtanding and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as the untemperate extravagants of ſome light perſon: yea further, they may beware (except they meane to deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all ſenſe of religion, and to pave their owne hearts, and to make them as the high way) how they bee converſant in them, and much more how they delight themſelves in that veine, but rather to turn
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:157702:8"/> their laughing into bluſhing, and to bee amazed as at a ſhort madneſſe, that they have in matters of religion, taken their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ſolace. But this perchance is one of thoſe faults which will bee ſooneſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, though I perceive never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, there wants not ſome which ſeeke to blanch and excuſe it. But to deſcend to a more narrow view and conſideration of the accidents and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of theſe controverſies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in either part deſerveth blame and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I finde generally in cauſes of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverſies, that men do offend in ſome or all of theſe five points:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt, the giving of occaſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to controverſies, and alſo the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ungrounded taking of the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next is the extending and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of controverſies to a more generall oppoſition and contradiction then appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth at the firſt propounding of them, when mens judgements are leaſt partiall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is the paſſionate and unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:157702:9"/> practiſes and proceedings on both parts towards the perſons each of others for their diſcredit and ſuppreſſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth, is the courſes holden and and entertained on either ſide, for the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the practizants to a more ſtreight uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within themſelves, which ever importeth a further deſtruction of the intire body.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt, is the undue and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent propounding, publiſhing, and debating of the controverſies. In which point the moſt palpable error hath been already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, as that which through the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and freſhneſſe of the abuſe firſt offereth it ſelfe to the conceits of all men.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the occaſion of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, it cannot be denied but that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection in the converſation and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe which have chiefe place in the Church, have ever been principall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and motives of ſchiſmes and diviſions: For whileſt the Biſhops and governours of the Church continue full of knowledge and good workes, whileſt they feed their flock indeed, while they deale with the ſecular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:157702:9"/> in all liberty and reſolution, according to the majeſty of their calling, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious care of ſoules impoſed upon them; ſo long the Church is ſituate, as it were, upon an hill, no man maketh queſtion of it, or ſeekes to depart from it: But when theſe vertues in the Fathers and Elders of the Church have loſt their light, and that they wax wordly, lovers of themſelves, and pleaſers of men: then men begin to grope for the Church as in the darke, they bee in doubt whether they bee the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles, or of the Phariſees; yea, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire, yet they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeake, <hi>tanquam authoritatem habentes,</hi> as having authority, becauſe they loſt their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the conſciences of men, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining their ſteppes from the way which they trace out to others; ſo as men have need continually ſounding in their eares, this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Nolite exire,</hi> goe not out, ſo ready are they to depart from the Church upon every voyce: And therefore it is truely noted by one who writeth as a naturall man, that the hypocriſie of Friers did for a great time,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:157702:10"/> maintaine and beare out the irreligion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prelates. For this is that double policie of the ſpiritual enemy, either by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit holineſſe of life to authorize and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh errors, or by the corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to diſcredit and call into queſtion truth and lawfull things.</p>
            <p>This concerneth my Lords the Biſhops, unto whom I am witneſſe to my ſelfe, that I ſtand affected as I ought: no contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath ſupplanted in mee the reverence I owe to their calling: neither hath any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction or calumnie embaſed my opinion of their perſons; I know ſome of them, whoſe names are moſt pierced with theſe accuſations, to be men of great vertues, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indiſpoſition of the time, and the want of correſpondence many wayes, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to fruſtrate the beſt indevours in the Church. And for the reſt generally, I can condemne none, I am no judge of them that belong to ſo high a maſter, neither have I two witneſſes: and I know it is truely ſaid of Fame, <hi>Pariter facta atque infecta canebat.</hi> Their taxations ariſe nor all from one coaſt:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:157702:10"/> They have indifferent enemies, and ready to invent ſlander, more ready to amplifie, and moſt ready to believe it, <hi>&amp; magnes mendacii credulitas,</hi> credulity is the allurement of lies. But if any be who have againſt the ſupreame Biſhops not a few things, but many: if any have loſt his firſt love, if any bee neither hot nor cold, if any have ſtumbled to folly at the threſhold, in ſuch ſort that he cannot ſit well that entred ill; it is time they returne whence they are fallen, and confirme the things which remaine. Great is the weight of this fault, <hi>Et eorum cauſa abhorrebant homines à ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificiis Domini:</hi> and for their cauſe did men abhor the worſhip of God. But howſoever it be, that thoſe have ſought to defame them, &amp; caſt contempt upon them, are not to beexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. It is the precept of <hi>Salomon, That the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers be not reproched, no not in thought,</hi> but that wee draw our conceit into a modeſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of their doings. The holy Angell would give no ſentence of blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common ſlanderer, but ſayd, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepet te Dominus,</hi> the Lord rebuke thee. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> thought againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157702:11"/> him that did polute ſacred juſtice with tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous violence, hee did juſtly denounce the judgement of God in faying, <hi>Percuciet te Dominus,</hi> the Lord ſhall ſtrike thee, yet in ſaying, <hi>Paries dealbate,</hi> he thogh the had gone too farre, and retracted it: whereupon a learned Father ſayd: <hi>Ipſum, quam vis inane, nomen &amp; umbram ſacerdotis cogitans expavit.</hi> The ancient Councels and Synods, as it is noted by the Eccleſiaſticall ſtory, when they deprived any Biſhop, never recorded the offence, but buried it in perpetuall ſilence. Onely <hi>Cham</hi> purchaſed his fathers curſe with revealing his fathers diſgrace: and yet a much greater fault is it, to aſcend from the perſon to the calling, and to draw that in queſtion. Many good Fathers rigorouſly compiained of the unworthineſſe of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as if it did preſently forfeit &amp; ceaſe their office. One ſayth: <hi>Sacerdotes nominamur &amp; non ſumus,</hi> we are called Prieſts, and are not. Another ſayth: <hi>niſi bonum opus amplectaris E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus eſſe non potes,</hi> except thou undertake the good worke, thou canſt not be a Biſhop; yet they meant nothing leſſe then to move
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157702:11"/> doubt of their calling or ordination?</p>
            <p>The ſecond occaſion of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troverſies, is, the nature &amp; humor of ſome men. The Church never wanteth a kinde of perſons that love the ſalutation of <hi>Rabbi,</hi> not in ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or complement, but in an inward autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which they ſeeke over mens mindes, in drawing them to depend upon their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo ſeeke knowledge at their lippes: theſe men are the true ſucceſſours of <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes,</hi> the lovers of preheminence, and not Lord Biſhops; ſuch ſpirits doe light upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſort of natures which doe adhere to theſe men, <hi>Quorum gloria in obſequio,</hi> ſtiffe fellowes, and ſuch as zeale marvellouſly for thoſe whom they have choſen to bee their maſters. This latter ſort of men for the moſt part, are men of young yeares, and ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall underſtanding, carried away with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall reſpect of perſons, or with the enticing appearance of godly names and pretences. <hi>Pauci res ipſas ſequuntur, plures nomina rerum; plurima nomina magiſtrorum:</hi> few follow the things themſelves, more the names of the things, moſt the names of their maſters.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:157702:12"/> About theſe general affections are wretched accidentall and private emulations and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentments. All which breake forth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into contentions, ſuch as either vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late truth, ſobriety, or peace. Theſe genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities apply themſelves. The Vniverſities are the ſeates and continent of this diſeaſe, whence it hath been, and is derived into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the realme. There ſome will be no longer <hi>è numero,</hi> of the number: there ſome others ſide themſelves before they know the right hand from the left. So as it is truely ſaid <hi>Tranſeunt ab ignorantia ad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicium:</hi> They leap from ignorance to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate opinion, and never take a good judgement in their way. But as it is wel no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: <hi>Inter juvenile judicium, &amp; ſenile prejudicium omnis veritas corrumpitur:</hi> When men are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different and not partiall, then their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is weake and unripe, through want of yeares; and when it groweth to ſtrength, and ripeneſſe, by that time it is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled with ſuch a number of prejudicate opinions, as it is made unprofitable, ſo as between theſe two all truth is corrupted;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:157702:12"/> while the honourable names of ſincerity, and reformation, and diſcipline, are put in the forward, ſo as contentions and evill zeales cannot be touched, except theſe holy thinges are firſt thought to be violated. But howſoever they ſhall inferre the ſolicitation for the peace of the Church: not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from carnall ſinnes: yet will I ever conclude with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul: Cum ſit inter vos zelus &amp; contentio, nonne carnales eſtis?</hi> While there is amongſt you zeale and contention, are ye not carnall? And howſoever they eſteem the compounding of controverſies, to ſavour of mens wiſedome and humane policie, I thinke themſelves led with the wiſedome which is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; yet I ſay with Saint <hi>Iames, Non eſt iſta ſapientia de ſurſum deſcendens, ſed terrena, animalis, diabolica. Ibi zelus &amp; contentio, ibi inconſtantia &amp; omne opus pravum.</hi> Of this inconſtancy it is ſaid by a learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Procedere non ad perfectionem, ſed ad permutationem.</hi> They ſeeke to goe forward ſtill, not to perfection, but to change.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:157702:13"/>
            <p>The third occaſion of controverſies, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be an extreame and unlimited dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of ſome former hereſie or corruption of the Church acknowledged &amp; convicted. This was the cauſe that produced the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Arrius,</hi> grounded chiefly upon dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of Gentiliſme; leſt the Chriſtians ſhould ſeeme by aſſertion of the coequall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of our Saviour Chriſt to approach to the acknowledgement of more Gods then one. The deteſtation of <hi>Arrius</hi> hereſie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced that of <hi>Sabellius,</hi> who holding for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable the diſſimilitude which <hi>Arri us</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the trinity, fled ſo farre from him, that he fell into the other extreame, to deny the diſtinction of perſons, and to ſay they were but onely names of ſeverall offices and diſpenſations; yea, moſt of the hereſies of the Church have ſprung up of this root, while men have made it their ſcale to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the bounds of their religion, taking it by the fartheſt diſtance from the errour laſt condemned. Theſe be <hi>Poſthumi haereſium filii,</hi> hereſies that ariſe of the aſhes of other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that are extinct and amortiſed. This
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:157702:13"/> manner of apprehenſion doth in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree poſſeſſe many of our time: they thinke it the true touch ſtone to try what is good and holy, by meaſuring what is more and leſſe oppoſite to the inſtitutions of the Church of Rome, be it ceremony, be it poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or government; yea be it other inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of greater weight, that is ever moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect which is removed moſt degrees from that Church; and that is ever polluted and blemiſhed which participateth in any appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with it: this is a ſubtile and dangerous conceit for men to entertaine, apt to delude themſelves, more apt to delude the people, and moſt apt of all to calumniate their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. This ſurely, but that a notorious condemnation of that poſition was laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, had long ſince brought us to the rebaptizing of children baptized accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the pretended Catholicke religion. For I ſee that which is a matter of much like reaſon, which is the reordaining of Prieſts, is a matter very reſolutely maintained. It is very meet that men beware how they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by this opinion, and that they know it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:157702:14"/> is a conſideration of much greater wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be well adviſed: whether in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall demolition of the inſtitutions of the Church of Rome, there were not (as mens actions are unperfect) ſome good purged with the bad, rather then to purge the Church as they pretend, every day anew, which is the way to make a wound in her bowels, as it is already begun.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt occaſion of theſe controverſies (a thing which did alſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Church in former time) is the partiall affectation and imitation of forraigne Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: for many of our men, during the time of perſecution, and ſince, having been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in Churches abroad, and received a great impreſſion of the government there ordained, have violently ſought to intrude the ſame upon our Church. But I anſwer, <hi>Conveniamus in eo quod convenit non in eo quod receptum eſt:</hi> let us agree in this with every Church, to doe that which is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the eſtate of it ſelfe, and not in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular cuſtomes. Although their Churches had received the better forme, yet many
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:157702:14"/> times it is to be ſought. <hi>Non quid optimum, ſed è bonis quid proximum:</hi> Not what is beſt, but of good things what is next and readieſt to be had. Our Church is not now to place, it is ſetled and eſtabliſhed. It may be in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill States a republique is better then a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: yet God forbid that lawfull king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſhould be tied to inovate and make alterations: <hi>Qui mala introducit, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Dei oppugnat revelatam in verbo: Qui nova introducit, voluntatem Dei oppugnat revelatam in rebus:</hi> He that bringeth in ill cuſtomes, reſiſteth the will of God revealed in his word: He that bringeth in new things, reſiſteth the will of God revealed in the things themſelves. <hi>Conſule providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Dei cum verbo Dei:</hi> Take counſaile of the providence of God, as well as of his word. Neither yet doe I admit that their forme (although it were posſible and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient) is better then ours, if ſome abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were taken away. The party and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality, is a thing of wonderfull great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and ſo is an ordinary government by Synods, which do neceſſarily enſue upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157702:15"/> the other. It is hard in all cauſes, eſpecially in matters of religion, when voyces ſhall bee numbred and not weighed. <hi>Equidem</hi> (ſaith a wiſe Father) <hi>ut verè quod res eſt ſcribam, prorſus decrevi fugere omnem conventum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nullius enim conſilii bonum exitum unqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vidi: conſilia enim non minuunt mala, ſed augent potius.</hi> To ſay the truth, I am utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined never to come to any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Biſhops: for I never yet ſaw good end of any Councell: for Councels abate not ill things, but rather increaſe them: which is not ſo much to bee underſtood of generall Councels, as for Synods ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered for the ordinary government of the Church, as for deprivation of Biſhops, or ſuch like caſes, which miſchiefe hath taught us the uſe of Archbiſhops and Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, and Primates, as the abuſe of them ſince hath cauſed men to miſlike them. But it will bee ſaid, Looke to the fruits of the Churches abroad and ours. To which I ſay, I beſeech the Lord to multiply his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings &amp; graces upon theſe an hundred fold. But yet it is not good we fall a numbring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157702:15"/> them. It may bee our peace hath made us wanton. It may be alſo (though I would be loath to derogate from the honor of thoſe Churches, were it not to remove ſcandals) that their fruits are as torches in the darke, which appeare greateſt a farre off. I know they may have ſome more ſtrict order for the repreſſing of ſundry exceſſes. But when I conſider of the cenſures of ſome perſons, as well upon particular men as upon Churches, I think of the ſaying of a Platoniſt, who ſaith: <hi>Certe vitia iraſcibilis partis animae ſunt gradu praviora quam concupiſcibilis tametſi oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultiora.</hi> A matter that appeared well by the ancient contentions of Biſhops: God grant we may contend with other Churches as the Vine with the Olive, which of us beareth beſt fruits: and not as the Brier with the Thiſtle, which of us is moſt unprofitable. And thus much touching the occaſion of controverſies.</p>
            <p>Now briefly to ſet down the growth and progreſſion of theſe controverſies, whereby will be verified the wiſe counſell of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that the courſe of contention is to bee ſtopped at the firſt, being elſe as the waters,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:157702:16"/> which if they get a breach, will hardly ever be recovered. It may be remembred, how that on their part who call for reformation, was firſt propounded ſome diſlike of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ceremonies, ſuppoſed to bee ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: ſome complained of dumb Miniſters, who poſſeſſed rich Benefices: ſome made invectives againſt the idle and monaſticall continuance within the Vniverſities, by thoſe who had livings to be reſident upon, and ſuch like cauſes. Thence they went on to condemne the government of Biſhops, as an Hierarchy remaining to us of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Romane Church, and to except to ſundry inſtitutions, as not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently delivered from the pollutions of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times. And laſtly, they are advanced to define of an onely and perpetuall forme of policie in the Church, which (without conſideration of the poſſibility, or foreſight of perill, or perturbation of the Church &amp; State) muſt be erected and planted by the Magiſtrate. Here they ſtay. Others not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keep footing on ſo ſteep a ground, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend further, that the ſame muſt bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:157702:16"/> into, and accepted by the people at their perill, without attending the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of authoritie; and ſo in the mean time they refuſe to communicate with us, reputing us to have no Church. This hath been the progreſſion of that ſide, I meane of the generality. For I know that ſome perſons (being of the nature not onely to love extremities, but to fall to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out degrees) were at the higheſt ſtreame at the firſt: the other part that maintaineth the preſent government of the Church, hath not kept one tenor neither. Firſt, thoſe ceremonies which they pretended to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, they maintained to bee things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and oppoſed the examples of the good times of the Church, to that chalenge that was made unto them, becauſe they were uſed in the latter ſuperſtitious times: then were they alſo content mildly to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge many imperfections in the Church, as Tares came up amongſt the Corne, which were not as yet according to the wiſedome of our Saviour Chriſt, to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtrife pulled up, leſt it might ſpoile and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:157702:17"/> ſupplant the good corn, but to grow on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till the harveſt. After this they grew to a more abſolute defence &amp; maintenance of orders of the Church: and ſtifly to hold that nothing was to be innovated, partly becauſe it needed not, and partly becauſe it would make a breach upon the reſt. Thence (exaſperate through contention) they are fallen to a direct condemnation of the contrary part, as of a ſect: yea and ſome indiſcreet perſons have been bold in open preaching to uſe diſhonourable and deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſpeech, and cenſure of the Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: and that ſo farre, as that ſome of our men (as I have heard) ordained in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne parts have beene pronounced to be no lawfull Miniſters. Thus we ſee the beginnings were modeſt, but the extreames violent: ſo as there is now almoſt as great a diſtance of either part from it ſelfe, as was at the firſt of one from the other. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (though my meaning and ſcope be not (as I ſaid before) to enter into the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies themſelves) yet I doe admoniſh the maintainers of the above named diſcipline,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:157702:17"/> to weigh and conſider ſeriouſly, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, how neer they are unto thoſe with whom I know they will not join. It is hard to ſay that the diſcipline which they ſay we want, is one of the Eſſentiall parts of the worſhip of God: and not to affirme, that the people upon perill of their ſalvation without ſtaying for the Magiſtrate are to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelves unto it. I demand if a civill State ſhould receive the preaching and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and exclude the ſacrament of the ſupper: were not men bound upon dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their ſoules, to draw themſelves to congregations, where they might celebrate that Miniſtery, and not content themſelves with that part of worſhip which the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate hath authoriſed? This I ſpeake not to draw them into miſlike of others, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a more deep conſideration of themſelves. <hi>Fortaſſe non redeunt, quia progreſſuum ſuum non intelligunt,</hi> Againe I ſay, to my Lords the Biſhops that it is heard for them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void blame in the opinion of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent perſon, in ſtanding ſo preciſely, in alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing. <hi>Leges novis legibus non
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:157702:18"/> recreate deſcunt,</hi> Lawes being not refreſhed with new lawes, wax ſowre. <hi>Qui mala non permutat, in bonis non perſeverat,</hi> without change of ill, a man can not continue the good: to take away abuſes, ſupplanteth not good orders, but eſtabliſhes them. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſa moris retentio res turbulenta aque ac no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas eſt,</hi> A contentious retaining of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome is a turbulent thing as well as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. A good husbandman is ever pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſtirring in his vineyard, or field; not unreaſonable indeed, nor unskilfully, for he lightly ever findeth ſomewhat to do. We have heard of no offers of the Biſhops of bils in Parliament, which no doubt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from them to whom it properly appertaineth, would have every where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived acceptation, their own conſtitutions, and orders have reformed little. Is nothing amiſſe? can any man defend the uſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, as a bare proceſſe to lackey up and downe, for duties and for fees, it being the greateſt judgement next unto that generall judgement at the laſt day? Is there no means to nurſe and traine up Miniſters?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:157702:18"/> (for the yeld of the Vniverſities will not ſerve, though they were never ſo well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned) to traine them I ſay not to preach (for that every man adventureth confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to doe) but to preach ſoundly and handle the Scriptures with wiſedome and judgement. I know Prophecying was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to great abuſes; and would be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed now, becauſe the leaſe of perſecution is encreaſed. But I ſay, the onely reaſon of the abuſe was, becauſe there were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to it a popular auditory, and it was conteined with a private conference of Miniſters. Other thinges might be ſpoken of. I pray God inſpire the Biſhops, with a fervent love, and care of the people, and that they may not ſo much urge thinges in controverſie, which all men confeſſe to bee gracious, and good. And thus much for the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>Now as to the third part of unbrother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceeding on either part, it is directly contrary to my purpoſe to amplifie wrongs, it is enough to note and number them:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:157702:19"/> which I doe alſo to move compaſſion and remorſe on the offending ſide, and not to animate chalenges and complaints on the other. And this point (as reaſon is) doth chiefly touch that ſide which doe moſt: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriae potentiorum ſunt,</hi> injuries come from them that have the upper hand; The wrongs of them that are oppreſſed, of the government of the Church towards the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may hardly bee diſſembled or excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: they have charged them as though they denied to pay tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and withdraw from the civill magiſtrate their obedience, which they ever performed and taught: They have ſorted and coupled them with the family of Love, whoſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies they have laboured to deſcry and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute: they have been ſwift of credit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive accuſations againſt them from thoſe that have quarrelled with them. But for ſpeaking againſt ſin and vice, their examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and inquiſitions have been ſtreight, ſwearing them to blanks &amp; generalities (not included within the compaſſe of matter cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, which the party that taketh the oath
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:157702:19"/> is able to comprehend) which is a thing cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and ſtrainable. Their urging of ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to their owne Articles, is but <hi>laceſcere &amp; irritare morbos Eccleſiae,</hi> which otherwiſe would ſpend and cruſh themſelves, <hi>Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum quaerit, ſed diſsidium auget, qui quod fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis praeſtatur, verbis exigit:</hi> hee ſeeketh not union but diviſion, which exacteth inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that, which men are content to yeeld in outward action. And it is true, there are ſome, which (as I am perſwaded) will not eaſily offend by inconformity, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding make ſome conſcience to ſubſcribe. For they know this note of inconſtancie &amp; defection from that which they have long held, ſhall diſable that good which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would do. For ſuch is the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of many, that they thinke their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries ſhould thereby be diſcredited. As for their eaſie ſilencing of them, in ſuch great ſcarcity of Preachers, is to puniſh the people and not them. Ought they not (I meane the Biſhops) to keep one eye open to looke upon the good that thoſe men do; not to fix them both upon the hurt that they ſuppoſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:157702:20"/> commeth by them. Indeed ſuch as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate and incorrigible God forbid they ſhould be permitted to teach. But ſhall every inconſiderate word, ſometimes captiouſly watched, and for the moſt part hardly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, be as it were a forfeiture of their voice &amp; gift in teaching? As for particular moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, I take no pleaſure to recite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhal be troubled for ſaying in Baptiſme, <hi>Do you believe?</hi> or, <hi>doſt thou believe?</hi> If another ſhal be troubled for praying for her Majeſty without addition of her ſtiles, whereas the very form of prayer in the book of <hi>Common prayer</hi> hath <hi>(thy ſervant Elizabeth)</hi> and no more. If a third ſhall be accuſed upon theſe words uttered touching the controverſies, <hi>Tollatur lex &amp; fiat certamen,</hi> whereby was meant, that the prejudice of the law remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, other reaſons ſhould be equally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of calling for mutinie and ſedition: as if he had ſaid, Away with the Law, and try it out by force. If theſe and other like parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars be true, which I have but by rumour, and cannot affirme, it is to bee lamented that they ſhould labour amongſt us with ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:157702:20"/> little comfort. I know reſtrained govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is better then remiſſe. And I am of his opinion that ſaid: <hi>Better it is to live where nothing is lawfull, then where all things are lawfull:</hi> I diſlike that lawes bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, or diſturbers unpuniſhed. But lawes are compared to the grape, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much preſſed, yeeldeth an hard and unwholeſome wine. Of theſe things I may ſay, <hi>Iram viri non operatur juſtitiam Dei:</hi> the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God. As for the injuries on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, they are, <hi>Ictus vermium,</hi> as it were headleſſe arrowes, they are fity and eager in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives: and in ſome fond men, uncivill and unreverent behaviour towards their perſons. This laſt invention alſo which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth them to deriſion and obloquie by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, chargeth (as I am perſwaded) the whole ſide; neither doth that other, which is yet more odious, practiſed by the moſt ſort of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is calling in as it were to their aid, certain mercenary bands, which impugned Biſhops &amp; other Eccleſiaſticall dignities, to have the ſpoile of their endowments and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:157702:21"/>
            <p>Of this I cannot ſpeake too hardly: It is an intelligence between incendiaries and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the one to rob or fire the houſe, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to rifle it. And thus much touching the third part.</p>
            <p>The fourth part wholly pertaineth to them which repugne the preſent Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call government, who although they have not cut themſelves from the body and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church: yet they effect cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cogniſants &amp; differences, wherein they ſeek to correſpond amongſt themſelves, and to differ from other: and it is truly ſaid, <hi>Tam ſunt mores Schiſmatici, quam dogmata Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica:</hi> There be as well Schiſmaticall factions as opinions. Firſt, they have impropered to themſelves the names of zealous, ſyncere, &amp; reformed, as if all other were cold, minglers of holy things, and prophane, and friends of abuſes. Yea to be a man endued with great vertues, and fruitfull in good workes, yet if he concurre not fully with them, they terme (inderogation) a civill and morall man, and compare him to <hi>Socrates</hi> or ſome heathen Phyloſopher: whereas the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:157702:21"/> of the Scripture teacheth us contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to denominate him religious accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the workes of the ſecond table: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they of the firſt are often counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and practiſed in hypocriſie. So ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that a man doth mainly boaſt of loving God whom he hath not ſeen, if he loveth not his neighbour whom he hath ſeen. And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, This is true religion to viſit the fatherleſſe and widow; and ſo that which is but Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall with them, is in the phraſe of the Apoſtle, true religion and Chriſtianity. As in affection they chalenge to themſelves the ſaid vertues of zeale, and the reſt, ſo in knowledge they attribute to themſelves light, and perfection. They ſay the Church of England in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of her Majeſties, was but in the cradle: and that the Biſhops of thoſe daies did ſomewhat for day-breake, but the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity and fulneſſe of light proceeded from themſelves. So <hi>Sabinus</hi> Biſhop of Heraclea of Macedonia, ſaid, that the Fathers in the councell of Nice were but infants, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:157702:22"/> men: that the Church was not ſo to perſiſt in their decrees, as to refuſe that far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ripneſſe of knowledge which the time had revealed. And as they cenſure vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men by the names of civill and moral, ſo doe they cenſure men truely, and godly-wiſe who ſee the vanity of their aſſertion) by the names of Politique, ſaying that their wiſedome is but carnall, and ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of mans braine. So likewiſe if a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher preach with care and meditation (I ſpeake not of the vaine Scholaſticall forme and manner of preaching) but ſoundly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ordering the matter he handleth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, and draweth it downe from au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſing of it by ſtrong proofes and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: they cenſure it as a forme of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, not becoming the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, and referre it to the reprehenſion of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the intiſing ſpeech of mans wiſedome. Now for their owne manner of preaching, what is it? Surely they exhort well, and worke compuction of minde, and bring men well to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Viri fratres quid agem us?</hi> but that is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:157702:22"/> not enough, except they reſolve this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They handle matters of controverſies weakly and <hi>obiter,</hi> and as before a people that will accept of any thing in doctrine or manners: there is little but generality and repetition. They move the bread of life, and toſſe it up and downe, they breake it not: They draw not their directions downe <hi>ad caſus conſcientiae,</hi> that a man may be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his particular actions whether they be lawfull or not; neither indeed are they able to doe it, what through want of grounded knowledge, what through want of ſtudy and time. It is an eaſie thing to call for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Sabbath day, and to ſpeake againſt unlawfull gaine: but what actions and workes may be done upon the Sabbath day, and in what caſes; and what courſes of gaine are lawfull, and what not: to ſet this downe, and to cleare ſo the whole matter with good diſtinctions and deciſions, is a matter of great knowledge and labour, and asketh much meditation and converſation in the Scriptures and other helpes which God hath provided &amp; preſerved for inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:157702:23"/> They carry not equall hand in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people their lawfull liberties as well as their reſtraints and prohibitions. But they thinke a man cannot goe too farre in keeping a commandement; they forget that there are ſinnes on the right hand as well as on the left, and that the ſword is double edged, and cutteth on both ſides, as well the ſuperſtitious obſervances, as the profane tranſgreſſions. Who doubteth but it is as unlawfull to ſhut where God hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, as to open where God hath ſhut? to binde where God hath looſed, and to looſe where God hath bound? Amongſt men it is as ill taken to turne backe favours, as to diſobey commandements. In this kinde of zeale (for example) they have pronounced generally and without difference all untruth is unlawfull, notwithſtanding that the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives have been reported to have been bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their excuſe, and <hi>Rahab</hi> is ſaid by faith to have concealed the ſpies. Farther, I heard ſome Sermons of mortification, which (I think) with very good meaning they have preached out of their owne experience and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:157702:23"/> exerciſe: and things in private counſell not unmeet, but ſurely no ſound conceits: much like to <hi>Parſons</hi> his Reſolutions, or not ſo good, rather apt to breed in men weak opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perplexed deſpaires, then filiall and true repentance which is ſought. Another point of great inconvenience and perill, is to intice the people to heare controverſies, and all manner of doctrine: they ſay no part of the counſell of God is to bee ſuppreſſed, nor the people defrauded. So as the difference which the Apoſtle maketh between milke and ſtrong meats, is confounded; and his precept that the weake bee not admitted to queſtions &amp; controverſies, taketh no place: But moſt of all it is to be ſuſpected as a ſeed of further inconvenience for manner of handling the Scriptures: for while they ſeek expreſſe Scripture for every thing; and that they have in a manner deprived themſelves and the Church of a ſpeciall helpe, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port by embracing the authority of Fathers, they reſort to naked examples, conceited in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and forced alluſions, ſuch as doe bring ruine to all certainty of Religion.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:157702:24"/>
            <p>Another extremity is that exceſſve magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of that, which though it be a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and holy inſtitution, yet hath limites as all things elſe have. We ſee (in a manner) whereſoever they find in the Scriptures the word ſpoken of, they expound it of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. They have made it almoſt of the Eſſence of the ſacrament of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to have a ſermon precedent. They have (in manner) annihilated liturgies and formes of divine ſervice. As for the life of the good Monkes and eremites of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, I know they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a man as halfe a Papiſt, if he ſhould maintaine them as other, then prophane, becauſe they heard no preaching. In the meane time, what preaching is, and who may be ſaid to preach, they make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. But as farre as I ſee every man that ſpeaketh in chaire is counted a preacher. But I am aſſured, that not a few that call wholly for a preaching miniſterie, deſerve to be of the firſt themſelves, that ſhould be expelled. Theſe and ſome other errors and miſproceedings, they doe fortifie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:157702:24"/> by being ſo greatly addicted to their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and impatient to heare contradiction or argument. Yea I know ſome of them, that would thinke is a tempting of God to heare or read what may be ſaid againſt them. As if there could be a <hi>Quod bonum è tenete,</hi> without an <hi>Omne probate</hi> going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This may ſuffice to offer unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a view and conſideration whether they do well or no, &amp; to correct &amp; aſſwage the partiallity of their followers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents. For as for any man that ſhall hereby enter into a contempt of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, it is but his owne hardneſſe of heart. I know the word of exhortation doth chiefly reſt upon theſe men, and they have zeale and hate of ſinne. But againe let them take heed that it be not true which one of their adverſaries ſaith againſt them, that they have but two ſmall wants, knowledge, and love. And ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the fourth part.</p>
            <p>The laſt point teaching the due publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and debating of theſe controverſies, needeth no long ſpeech. this ſtrange abuſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:157702:25"/> of Antiques and Paſquils hath been tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before. So likewiſe I repent not that which I ſaid before, that a character of love is more proper for debates of this nature, then that of zeale. As for all direct and direct glaunces or levels of mens perſons, they were ever in theſe caſes diſallowed. Laſtly, whatſoever is pretended, the people is no meet judge or arbitrator; but rather the moderate, quiet, and private aſſemblies of the learned. <hi>Qui apud in capace loquitur non diſceptat, ſed calumniatur.</hi> The Preſſe &amp; Pulpit would be morefreed and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: neither promotion on the one ſide, nor glory and heat on the other, ought to continue theſe chalenges at the Groſſe, and ſuch places. But rather all Preachers eſpecially ſuch as are of a good temper, and have wiſedome, with conſcience ought to inculcate and beat upon a place, peace, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſufferance. Neither let them feare <hi>Solons</hi> law which compelled in facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, every particular perſon to range him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on the one ſide, or the other: nor the fond calumnie of neutrality. But let them know
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:157702:25"/> that it was true which was ſaid by a wiſe man, that neuters in contention were better or worſe, then either ſide.</p>
            <p>Theſe things have I in all ſyncerity and ſimplicity, ſet downe touching the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies which now trouble the Church of England, and that without all art or inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation: and therefore not likely to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to either part. Notwithſtanding I truſt what hath been ſaid, ſhall finde a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in their minde, who are not embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with partiality, and which love the whole better then the part. Whereby I am not out of hope that it may doe good. At leaſt I ſhall not repent my ſelfe of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
